Southern New England Telephone Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Southern New England Telephone Company Records.
undated, 1877-2003.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Southern New England Telephone Company.
631 linear feet.
MSS19970122
Established in January 1878 as the District Telephone Company of New Haven [Connecticut]; opened the world's first telephone exchange that same year. Reorganized as the Southern New England Telephone Company in 1882.
History
Chronology
1878 January 15, The District Telephone Company of New Haven was incorporated. January 28, World's first commercial exchange opened in New Haven, Connecticut. February 21, World's first directory issued in New Haven. April 15, World's first private Toll line put into service, Blackrock to Bridgeport. April 15, World's first telephone booth. May 28, Reorganization as The Connecticut District Telephone Company. June 15, World's first commercial toll line is put into service: Springfield to Holyoke, Massachusetts. October 12, Name changed to The District Telephone and Automatic Signal Company.
1879 March 24, Connecticut's first woman operator, Marjorie Gray was hired in Bridgeport.
1880 Reorganization as The Connecticut Telephone Company.
1882 October 2, Southern New England Telephone Company was incorporated.
1889 World's first coin-box telephone.
1922 June 10, Connecticut's first dial unit cut into service in Hartford.
1945 October 21, SNET 500,000th telephone installed.
1953 First major telephone company to complete dial service.
1956 One millionth phone installed.
1962 December 9, Connecticut becomes the first state to be completely direct distance dialing.
1967 Electronic switching is introduced in Connecticut.
1970 Two millionth phone installed. May; as a residential trial, SNET was the first company to offer call waiting, call forwarding and conference calling. The service was called “Totalphone.”
1979 November 15, the first company to use fiber optics in local telephone exchange.
1984 Bell System Divestiture. December, Introduced the first fiber optic backbone system to serve a state communication network.
1986 Holding company structure approved by the DPUC: Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation created. Completes an enhanced statewide 911 emergency system - the third in the nation.
1994 I-SNET, the first broadband information superhighway introduced.
1996 June 25, Introduction of one-second billing. September 25, SNET granted the first statewide video franchise in the United States.
1998 October 26, SNET merged with SBC Communications Inc.
On 27 April 1877, Alexander Graham Bell gave a demonstration of his new invention, the telephone, at Skiff's Opera House in New Haven, Connecticut. This presentation piqued the interest and ingenuity of George Coy, a civil war veteran and manager for the Atlantic and Pacific Telegraph Company. On 3 November 1877, George Coy was awarded a Bell telephone franchise for New Haven and Middlesex counties. This franchise stipulated that the Bell Company would own thirty-five percent of Coy's enterprise. This relationship was maintained for most of the history of the company.
Using carriage bolts, teapot lids and wire, Coy improvised a crude switchboard with 8 lines, each of which could serve up to 8 customers. Coy enlisted the financial backing of Herrick Frost, a prominent businessman, and Walter Lewis, superintendent of the New Haven Clock Company. On 15 January 1878, with the help of a young lawyer, Morris Tyler, the New Haven District Telephone Company was incorporated. On 28 January of that same year, the first commercial exchange was opened in New Haven with 21 customers. On 11 February the new company published the world's first classified telephone directory. The directory listed 50 customers.
The company reorganized several times over the next few years, seeking to raise money with larger capitalization to expand its territory and broaden franchise rights with the Bell Company in Boston. During this time, the company took over the pioneering exchanges in Hartford, Meriden and Bridgeport and began to build and promote toll lines. It is also of note that during this period the first woman operator in Connecticut, Marjorie Gray, was hired in Bridgeport. Despite this expansion, competition was so fierce Coy and Frost were compelled to sell controlling interest in the company to financier Jay Gould who in turn, used the company in a bid to gain control of Western Union. By the end of 1879, Western Union had conceded the telephone business to Bell in exchange for an agreement that the Bell companies would stay out of the telegraph business. Because of this settlement, Gould lost interest in the fledgling Telephone Company. In the meantime, Coy and Frost had approached Marshall Jewell, a former state governor, Postmaster General, ambassador, and chairman of the Republican National Committee to help raise money to, once again, raise capitol by reorganizing the company. In 1880, the company was reorganized as the Connecticut Telephone Company with Marshall Jewell as its president. A portion of the funds raised were used to buy out Gould's share, thus making the company wholly controlled by Connecticut investors again.
Within the next two years, the company was running twenty-four exchanges connected by toll lines and had over 3500 customers. A subsidiary company, the Inter State Telephone Company, had begun construction of a line between Boston and New York. And in 1882, the company was reorganized, yet again, as the Southern New England Telephone Company. Much expansion was envisioned for the company.
Two developments soon put a damper on the intended growth. The widespread introduction of electricity caused interference on the telephone lines. The problem necessitated a costly solution - the connection of every customer with “metallic circuits”: two copper wires rather then a single iron one. This also required the replacement of every switchboard. The second development was the failure of the New York-Boston line. The line was sold to the newly incorporated long-distance company, American Telephone & Telegraph. SNET also sold off its Massachusetts holdings for much needed capitol and made the decision to limit its operations to Connecticut.
The remainder of the 1880s was a period of very little growth and expensive equipment upgrades resulting in a period of severely limited company earnings. Problems were compounded by the Blizzard of 1888, which took down many wires and poles in the outlying areas. However, the 1890s ushered in a period of strong growth as the American economy began to expand rapidly. The number of telephones nearly tripled to just over 15,000 as rates were reduced and an advertising campaign began. Debts were paid off and dividends to shareholders were reinstated. During this time, Bell Company patents ran out and competition again became fierce. In 1899, the Connecticut Legislature recognized the monopolistic nature of the telephone business and passed laws creating barriers to the entrance of new companies. In 1911, this law was replaced by a Public Utilities Commission, which had the power to regulate rates and services for SNET and other utilities. With this help the company grew rapidly throughout the first years of the twentieth century.
During World War I, SNET suffered shortages of material and employees as resources were diverted to the war effort. Operators were hard to find and 50 men were sent to the Army Signal Corps. In 1918, the federal government assumed control of all telephone and telegraph companies. Before the companies were returned a year later, the government had instituted the first nationwide rate increase in an effort to cover costs of operation. SNET was left with a large backlog of service requests at the war's end.
Business picked up again in the 1920s as the conversion to dial service, which eliminated the need to go through an operator, was begun. But expansion was again halted when the stock market crashed in 1929 and the Great Depression ensued. The 1930s saw the first net loss of telephones since 1894. The dividend was reduced, sales efforts were stepped up, and lay-offs were only avoided by reducing work schedules. Also, in 1938 SNET saw one of its worst natural disasters. The Hurricane of '38 knocked out nearly a third of the telephones in the region and left 62 of 79 central offices without power. With the help of other Bell companies, SNET was able to reconnect all of its customers in 23 days.
World War II brought many of the same problems as the first World War. Over 740 SNET employees entered the military. During the war, only 4 party residence service was available, leaving the company with a backlog of 60,000 customers waiting for private service. In addition, inflation and high income taxes left the company's financial stability in question at the war's end. In 1947, SNET applied for, and was granted, its first rate increase in 20 years.
During the post-war years the economy, and the telephone business, grew rapidly. 500,000 phones were in service in 1945 and by 1956 the one million mark was surpassed. The conversion to the dial system was completed in 1953 and in 1956 an improved dial system called “crossbar” was implemented. By 1970 there were two million telephones in service. At this time the company underwent a concerted effort to centralize service for increased efficiency and simplified long-distance services.
In 1974, SNET's corporate parent, AT&T, was sued by the federal government to break up the Bell System monopoly on the telephone industry. In a 1982 settlement AT&T was required to spin off its local telephone companies to shareholders. The local telephone companies were prohibited from engaging in any other business except local exchange service until January 1984. Because SNET was only 22% owned by AT&T at the time of the agreement, the company was not required to comply with this ruling. In response, on 1 January 1983, SNET established the Sonecor Systems Division in order to take advantage of their special status. This subsidiary would distribute equipment made by a variety of different manufacturers. In August 1983, SNET announced a artnership with CSX, a railroad holding company, to build a network of fiber optic cables, called Lightnet, which was planned to link 43 cities in 24 states along the railroad right-of-ways. In February 1984, AT&T announced the sale of its SNET shares. A relationship that had lasted over a hundred years had ended.
In 1986, SNET reorganized its corporate structure once again to reflect its new diversified nature. The newly formed holding company would be able to better manage the new divisions and would now be called the Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation. In 1988, SNET formed a partnership with NYNEX to offer cellular service and in 1989 sold their share of Lightnet for $365 million dollars to Williams Communications. By the end of the decade, SNET had more then doubled its 1980 income level.
In 1991, amidst economic recession, SNET received its first rate increase in 10 years. During this year the company also established a new subsidiary, SNET Paging, Inc. which would offer paging service to Connecticut, Rhode Island and Boston.
The next seven years were a period of new product and service introductions for the company, including SNET 800 CustomLink (800 numbers for residence customers) and Smartlink, which included services such as Caller ID. In 1993, SNET announced plans to invest 4.5 billion dollars in I-SNET, a statewide, interactive information super highway, and launched SNET America, which would offer national and international long distance calling. This year also saw the beginning of an effort to downsize in order to reduce operating costs. Two thousand five hundred people were slated to leave the company by 1995. The introduction of SNET Internet came in 1995 and in 1996, SNET led the industry with the introduction of one-second billing. In 1997, J.D. Power and Associates rated SNET as the number one rated long-distance company in America. And in that same year SNET Americast, a cable television service, was launched. In addition, the acquisition of Woodbury Telephone Company, the only other independent telephone company in Connecticut, was completed.
On 5 January 1998, a transaction was announced that would merge the Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation and SBC Communications Inc., of San Antonio, Texas. On 26 October, after approval from stockholders, the FCC and CDPUC, the merger was officially completed. Although operating headquarters remained in Connecticut and the SNET name was retained, the company had officially come to the end of its days as an independent telecommunications service provider.
Scope and Content
The records of the Southern New England Telephone Company (SNET) reflect the long history of a pioneering and innovative telephone company. The collection consists of material dating from the formation of the New Haven District Telephone Company and the invention of the switchboard in 1878 to the merger of the Southern New England Telecommunications Corporation and SBC Communications Inc. in 1998. However, the bulk of the material predates the 1983 Bell System divestiture.
The collection covers a wide range of records from SNET. It is particularly strong in advertising material with print, radio, and television information spanning sixty years from 1920 to 1980, early financial data, and photographic material that depict not only the business but the entire state of Connecticut. The company also kept an extensive file of “historical material” which contains town histories, exchange histories, personal recollections of key figures, and information about storms and disasters. The early correspondence found in Series I, Administration/Business, provides an interesting glimpse into the development of the telephone business and the telephone's acceptance in society. Of special interest might also be the records of the predecessor and subsidiary companies of SNET. The collection also includes a substantial set of directories ranging from 1878 to the 1960s. Included with the directories is the only known copy of the first directory ever printed.
The collection, however, has several gaps. The collection does not contain a substantial amount of personnel material. What few items there are can be found in Series I, Administration/Business. There is virtually no information on labor relations and there is very little information of a technical nature, or on product development.
Arrangement
The collection is broken down into twelve series. The first five series reflect a breakdown loosely based on the 1991 SNET records management schedule. The remaining series are based on a pre-existing order or format.
Administration/Business (1877-1980)
Accounting/Finance (1882-1985)
Corporate Relations (1915-1995)
Product Service Development (1889-1942)
Studies, Reports and Plans (1911-1985)
Subject Files (1879-2003)
Publications (1878-1998)
Predecessor and Subsidiary Companies (1878-1979)
Memorabilia, Artifacts, and Artwork (1904-1990s)
Audio/Visual (1951-2003)
Photographs (1878-1998)
Restricted Material
Series I: Administration / Business ( undated, 1877-1980 ) contains three subseries: Administration, Business-corporation, and Business - General. All are organized alphabetically. The first two subseries are based loosely on the 1991 SNET records management schedule. Administration primarily contains material such as correspondence, organizational charts, and procedure manuals. The correspondence files in this subseries formerly existed four ways. There was loose material, material indexed by letter in boxes, letterpress books, and binders of “executive letters.” The loose material and the boxed material are interfiled chronologically. The bindered material and letterpress books follow the loose material. The boxed material often contained additional material such as reports, contracts, receipts, and bills. For those boxes indexed by letter, major contributors to a section are listed in parentheses. Additional material may exist in each section. The Business - Corporation subseries contains material such as annual reports, minutes, by-laws, material associated with capitol stock, contracts and agreements and other material pertaining to the condition of the company. The Business - General subseries contains records that do not clearly indicate departmental provenance but do pertain to the workings of the business. For example, this subseries contains files on the purchase of other companies, records pertaining to rate issues such as rate increase cases and directory assistance charging, and material associated with the 1969-72 sale of the TWX system. A minimal amount of personnel material is also located in the subseries.
Series I: Administration / Business.
Series II: Accounting / Finance ( undated, 1882-1985 ) contains six subseries arranged alphabetically; A.J. Alex, Chief Accountant-Comptrollers Office; Bound Volumes; Depreciation Accounting; General Accounting; Insurance; and Private Mobile Radio Loss. Oversized materials are listed at the end of the series. The A.J. Alex subseries dates from 1893 to 1958 with the bulk of material covering 1923 to 1958. The records are listed in the original numbered order from 1.01 to 114.1 with a gap from 71-112. Headings follow each number and summarize the foldered materials. There is no index. The records consist of memoranda, correspondence, notes, plans, diagrams, bills, deeds, procedures, brochures, contracts, studies, estimates, letters, orders, directives, reports, records, regulations, and minutes. The topics cover a wide range of issues pertaining to SNET accounting such as: holiday pay, billing, benefits, rates, contracts, government regulations, war-time procedures, office supplies fleet cars, and coin telephones. The Bound Volumes subseries spans 1882 to 1985, but the bulk of the materials date from 1882 to 1920. The subseries consists of books, journal, ledgers, and boxed folders and bound books arranged alphabetically. The topics include cash records, expenses, reports, vouchers, trial balances, spending, debits and credits, and accounts payable and receivable. The subseries provides an overall picture of early SNET spending, costs, and financing.
The Depreciation Accounting subseries dates from 1912 to 1981 and deals with material and equipment depreciation. Correspondence, minutes, instructions, reports, and procedures make up the bulk of the subseries, which is arranged alphabetically. The General Accounting subseries covers a 100-year time frame, from 1883-1983. It contains SNET bills/receipts, transfers, records, taxes, correspondence, and procedures. Sections of Circulars and Handbooks provide information about SNET general accounting methods and practices. The Insurance subseries spans 1921 to 1967, with the bulk of the information occurring from 1948 to 1967. The materials consist of policies, data, schedules, correspondence, bonds, fire and equipment insurance, statistics, leases, city/town insurance, and reports. The subseries is also alphabetically arranged, as is the Private Mobile Radio Loss subseries. A box of Mobile Private Radio Loss index cards is listed separately at the end of the subseries. The subseries focuses on SNET financial losses with Private Mobile Radio phones from 1951 to 1964.
Series II: Accounting / Finance.
Series III: Corporate Relations ( undated, 1915-1995 ) is divided into four subseries: Advertising, Customer Complaints, Employee Information, and Public Information. The series is arranged alphabetically. Advertising covers the period from 1924 to 1988. The subseries contains material pertaining to SNET advertising campaigns such as correspondence, schedules, meeting minutes, programs, research, and studies from 1965 to 1980. Advertising budget and Yellow Page budget information is available from 1970 through 1980. The subseries is particularly strong in the decades of the 1960s and 1970s, with specific campaigns such as those for Business, Residence, UCONN Basketball and Football, and Long Distance Calling. Information such as correspondence, memoranda, and planning is also available for SNET promotions for such products as the Decorator Telephone, Calling Card, and Phone Store, 1968 to 1977. Newspaper ad samples are available from 1924 to 1931 as well as advertising samples labeled “Printed Material for Clients” produced by SNET from 1986 to 1988. There is extensive information for Yellow Pages advertising from 1973 to 1980 including studies, research, correspondence, and campaigns. The oversized material consists of original illustrations and artwork from the 1950s through the 1980s. Mechanicals, photographs, printing plates, and posters pertaining to advertisements are also included. Large binders contain sample advertisements ranging from 1955 to 1980 that reflect the cultural and social changes in Connecticut.
The Customer Complaint subseries does not have information on the department structure or policies. There is a Customer Comment Guide dated 1930. Most of the materials are contained in binders consisting of customer complaints to the Federal Communications Commission (1949-1969) and customer complaints and problems on rates, service, and equipment reported to the Connecticut State Public Utilities Commission (1915-1971). The subseries does not include correspondence from SNET to the customers or commissions. The Employee Information subseries is comprised of memoranda, correspondence, and plans for SNET personnel programs and some information on company policy (1970-1988). Programs and policies addressed areas such as: Ecology, Fitness, and Safety. There is a unique and interesting collection of Safety Cards promoting employee health, awareness, and safety from 1935 to 1965. Two oversized binders contain similar material. There is very little information of department structure, labor/management relations, or personnel policies and procedures. The series concludes with the Public Information subseries (1968-1995). This subseries consists of materials relating to promoting the SNET corporate image and public relations. Programs such as Corporate Symbol, Ecology, and Centennial contain correspondence, plans, and announcements (1968-1991). There is a collection of interviews with SNET Directors from 1976 to 1977. News releases, news conferences, and press luncheons are included from 1974 to 1992. A strength of this subseries is the collection of speeches, by top executives, that demonstrate SNET's commitment to public relations and community involvement (1965- 1987). The oversized material consists of informational packages dealing with topics such as the Centennial Celebration, Links To Learning Program, and World's Fair Promotion. Included in these packages are promotional items, announcements, program descriptions, and brochures (1964-1995).
Series III: Corporate Relations.
Series IV: Product Service Development ( undated, 1889-1942 ) is also based on the 1991 SNET records management schedule. This series is arranged alphabetically. It contains blueprints and diagrams from approximately 1889 to 1921. Included are diagrams of the Court Street building in New Haven, the Stamford dial office, the Grey Rock Place building in Stamford, a blueprint of the Coy switchboard, and others. The series also contains scattered engineering and plant records from the early twentieth century.
Series IV: Product Service Development.